<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: mac | Cocoa Factory]]></title>
  <link href="http://cocoa-factory.github.com/blog/categories/mac/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://cocoa-factory.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-19T10:54:29-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://cocoa-factory.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alan Duncan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to use custom NSAttributedString attributes]]></title>
    <link href="http://cocoa-factory.github.com/blog/2012/10/29/how-to-use-custom-nsattributedstring-attributes/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-29T19:36:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://cocoa-factory.github.com/blog/2012/10/29/how-to-use-custom-nsattributedstring-attributes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>How to draw a custom attribute in <code>NSLayoutManager</code></h2>

<p>The Cocoa Text System is incredibly flexible; but not nearly as well-documented as it should be given its power.  The classes and methods themselves are completely documented as is the "big picture" - but there's a lot of intermediate documentation that's missing.</p>

<p>In this tutorial, we'll build an app that draws a custom attribute in an <code>NSTextView</code> like this:</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/mErdK.png" alt="CustomAttributeTestApp" /></p>

<p><code>NSAttributedString</code> is great for drawing standard attributes such as font, font size, foreground and background colors; but it gets more complicated when you need to some something that requires actual drawing.  This tutorial will show you how to do simple drawing of a custom attribute.</p>

<h3>Getting Started</h3>

<p>Download the <a href="https://github.com/cocoa-factory/CCFCustomAttributeTutorial/zipball/master">example project</a> from Github.  You need Xcode 4.5 for this project; so if you don't have it - go update Xcode first.</p>

<h3><code>NSAttributedString</code> for decorated text</h3>

<p><code>NSAttributedString</code> and its mutable counterpart <code>NSMutableAttributedString</code> are used to draw decorated text.  Using these classes, you can create strings with attributes that describe how the string should look when drawn.  For example, you can add font and color attributes like this:</p>

<p>``` objc
NSString <em>sampleString = @"This is a sample string";
NSAttributedString </em>attributedString;
attributedString = [[NSAttributedString alloc] initWithString:sampleString</p>

<pre><code>                                               attributes:@{NSFontSizeAttribute:@24}];
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>This creates a string whose font size attribute is 24.0 pt.  And if we want to display the <code>attributedString</code> in an <code>NSTextView</code>:</p>

<p><code>objc
NSTextView *textView;
[textView setAttributedString:attributedString];
</code></p>

<p>With the mutable variant <code>NSMutableAttributedString</code> you can add and remove attributes dynamically:</p>

<p>``` objc
NSMutableAttributedString *string;
string = [[NSMutableAttributedString alloc] initWithString:@"The quick brown fox"</p>

<pre><code>          attributes:@{NSBackgroundColorAttributeName : [NSColor yellowColor]}];
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>which will render like this:</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/qMnbA.png" alt="background-color" /></p>

<p>Of course, you can also combine attributes:</p>

<p>``` objc
NSMutableDictionary *attributes = [[NSMutableDictionary alloc] init];</p>

<pre><code>[attributes setObject:[NSColor yellowColor] forKey:NSBackgroundColorAttributeName];

NSFont *font = [[NSFontManager sharedFontManager] fontWithFamily:@"Arial" traits:0 weight:5 size:24];
[attributes setObject:font forKey:NSFontAttributeName];
NSMutableAttributedString *string;
string = [[NSMutableAttributedString alloc] initWithString:@"The quick brown fox"
                                                attributes:attributes];
[[self textView] insertText:string];
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/J4EWm.png" alt="Combining attributes" /></p>

<h3><code>NSMutableAttributedString</code> tracks changes to its string</h3>

<p>If you want to change the underlying <code>NSMutableAttributedString</code> without disturbing its attributes, you can use its <code>mutableString</code> method to obtain an <code>NSMutableString</code> that you can manipulate behind its back, while the <code>NSMutableAttributedString</code> tracks the changes.  In fact the object you get back from <code>mutableString</code> is not actually an instance of <code>NSMutableString</code> but an instance of <code>NSMutableStringProxyForMutableAttributedString</code> instead.  This proxy object is responsible for the tracking behavior internally.</p>

<h3>What about custom attributes, then?</h3>

<p>Let's get started building the custom attribute.  The drawing is done in the context of a layout manager - a subclass of <code>NSLayoutManager</code> Since our intent is to use our custom attribute in the context of an <code>NSTextView</code> we should look at the architecture of that class first.  <code>NSTextView</code> has a single text container in which is lays out text.  The <code>NSTextContainer</code> is a rectangular region in which to layout text.  Each <code>NSTextView</code> has a default text container, but it is possible to replace the text container using the <code>replaceTextContainer</code> method.  The text container uses a layout manager to layout and draw the text.  There is readonly access to the text container's layout manager on <code>NSTextView</code>.  In order to give <code>NSTextView</code> a new layout manager, we have to set it on a new <code>NSTextContainer</code> object.</p>

<p>So let's start with a custom text view that we'll call <code>CCFTextView</code>.  You can find the source code in the "view" folder.  This text view basically does on thing - replace its <code>NSLayoutManager</code></p>

<p>``` objc
static CCFTextView <em>commonInit(CCFTextView </em>self) {</p>

<pre><code>//  set up our initial text size
NSFont *font = [[NSFontManager sharedFontManager] fontWithFamily:@"Helvetica" traits:0 weight:5 size:24.0];
NSDictionary *attributes = @{NSFontAttributeName : font};
[self setTypingAttributes:attributes];

//  replace our layout manager with custom layout manager
CCFCustomLayoutManager *layoutManager = [[CCFCustomLayoutManager alloc] init];
NSTextContainer *textContainer = [[NSTextContainer alloc] init];

[self replaceTextContainer:textContainer];
[textContainer replaceLayoutManager:layoutManager];
return self;
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>The <code>commonInit</code> function is called from either <code>initWithCoder:</code> or <code>initWithFrame:</code> so that no matter how the <code>CCFTextView</code> gets initialized, we replace its text container's layout manager with our own subclass.  Let's look at the <code>NSLayoutManager</code> subclass - <code>CCFCustomLayoutManager</code> in the "helpers+managers" directory.  In the header file "CCFCustomLayouManager.h" we define a few constants.  <code>CCFSpecialHighlighterAttributeName</code> is the name of our custom attribute and <code>CCFHighlightColorKey</code> and <code>CCFLineColorKey</code> are keys to the dictionary value of our attribute.</p>

<p>In the implementation of our layout manager, we override a single method <code>drawGlyphsForGlyphRange:atPoint:</code>.  Here we'll digress about glyphs vs. characters.</p>

<h3>Glyphs versus characters</h3>

<p>The <strong>character</strong> can is the smallest unit of a written language that has meaning.  In Roman and other alphabets, it maps to a particular sound in the spoken counterpart of the written language.  However in the case of other languages, like Chinese, it can represent an entire word.</p>

<p>A <strong>glyph</strong> on the other hand is a graphically-concrete form of a character.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/3z2M5.png" alt="Glyphs-vs-characters" /></p>

<p>The distinction is important, because while we're manipulating characters in our code, the text system is working behind the scenes laying out glyphs, not characters.  In this case, we need to do both.  That's why out <code>NSLayoutManager</code> subclass overrides <code>drawGlyphsForGlyphRange:atPoint</code>.  So let's look a little more closely at what we do in this method, which we'll build up from pseudo-code</p>

<p>``` objc
- (void)drawGlyphsForGlyphRange:(NSRange)glyphsToShow atPoint:(NSPoint)origin {</p>

<pre><code>/*
    iterate over our glyph ranges
    map the glyph range back to the character range that it represents
    check if our attribute is set on the character range
    if attribute is set
        get the rect of where we should draw the glyph
        do our drawing
*/
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>First, since we need to refer to the character sequence when we do the mapping, we need a source for that mapping.  Fortunately, <code>NSLayoutManager</code> keeps a reference to its <code>NSTextStorage</code> object.  This object is a subclass of <code>NSMutableAttributedString</code>.  We will get this reference and copy <code>glyphsToShow</code> to a local variable so that we can iterate over its span.</p>

<p>``` objc
- (void)drawGlyphsForGlyphRange:(NSRange)glyphsToShow atPoint:(NSPoint)origin {</p>

<pre><code>NSTextStorage *textStorage = self.textStorage;
NSRange glyphRange = glyphsToShow;
while (glyphRange.length &gt; 0) {
    /*
    map the glyph range back to the character range that it represents
    check if our attribute is set on the character range
    if attribute is set
        get the rect of where we should draw the glyph
        do our drawing
    */
}
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Now, we take care of the glyph-to-character mapping:</p>

<p>``` objc
- (void)drawGlyphsForGlyphRange:(NSRange)glyphsToShow atPoint:(NSPoint)origin {</p>

<pre><code>NSTextStorage *textStorage = self.textStorage;
NSRange glyphRange = glyphsToShow;
while (glyphRange.length &gt; 0) {
    NSRange charRange = [self characterRangeForGlyphRange:glyphRange actualGlyphRange:NULL];
    NSRange attributeCharRange, attributeGlyphRange;
    id attribute = [textStorage attribute:CCFSpecialHighlightAttributeName
                                  atIndex:charRange.location longestEffectiveRange:&amp;attributeCharRange
                                  inRange:charRange];
    attributeGlyphRange = [self glyphRangeForCharacterRange:attributeCharRange actualCharacterRange:NULL];
    attributeGlyphRange = NSIntersectionRange(attributeGlyphRange, glyphRange);
    /*
    check if our attribute is set on the character range
    if attribute is set
        get the rect of where we should draw the glyph
        do our drawing
    */
}
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Then to check if the attribute is set on this <code>charRange</code>, we just test for non-nil:</p>

<p>``` objc
- (void)drawGlyphsForGlyphRange:(NSRange)glyphsToShow atPoint:(NSPoint)origin {</p>

<pre><code>NSTextStorage *textStorage = self.textStorage;
NSRange glyphRange = glyphsToShow;
while (glyphRange.length &gt; 0) {
    NSRange charRange = [self characterRangeForGlyphRange:glyphRange actualGlyphRange:NULL];
    NSRange attributeCharRange, attributeGlyphRange;
    id attribute = [textStorage attribute:CCFSpecialHighlightAttributeName
                                  atIndex:charRange.location longestEffectiveRange:&amp;attributeCharRange
                                  inRange:charRange];
    attributeGlyphRange = [self glyphRangeForCharacterRange:attributeCharRange actualCharacterRange:NULL];
    attributeGlyphRange = NSIntersectionRange(attributeGlyphRange, glyphRange);

    if( attribute != nil ) {
        /*
            get the rect of where we should draw the glyph
            do our drawing
        */
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Finally, the drawing is the easiest part.  We just need to bracket our drawing code with calls to save then restore the <code>NSGraphicsContext</code> before drawing.  To get the rectangle in which our glyph is drawn, we ask for the <code>boundingRectForGlyphRange:inTextContainer:</code>.  Lastly, we have our completed implementation:</p>

<p>``` objc
- (void)drawGlyphsForGlyphRange:(NSRange)glyphsToShow atPoint:(NSPoint)origin {</p>

<pre><code>NSTextStorage *textStorage = self.textStorage;
NSRange glyphRange = glyphsToShow;
while (glyphRange.length &gt; 0) {
    NSRange charRange = [self characterRangeForGlyphRange:glyphRange actualGlyphRange:NULL];
    NSRange attributeCharRange, attributeGlyphRange;
    id attribute = [textStorage attribute:CCFSpecialHighlightAttributeName
                                  atIndex:charRange.location longestEffectiveRange:&amp;attributeCharRange
                                  inRange:charRange];
    attributeGlyphRange = [self glyphRangeForCharacterRange:attributeCharRange actualCharacterRange:NULL];
    attributeGlyphRange = NSIntersectionRange(attributeGlyphRange, glyphRange);
    if( attribute != nil ) {
        [NSGraphicsContext saveGraphicsState];

        NSColor *bgColor = [attribute objectForKey:CCFHighlightColorKey];
        NSColor *lineColor = [attribute objectForKey:CCFLineColorKey];

        NSTextContainer *textContainer = self.textContainers[0];
        NSRect boundingRect = [self boundingRectForGlyphRange:attributeGlyphRange inTextContainer:textContainer];

        [bgColor setFill];
        NSRectFill(boundingRect);

        NSRect bottom = NSMakeRect(NSMinX(boundingRect), NSMaxY(boundingRect)-1.0, NSWidth(boundingRect), 1.0f);
        [lineColor setFill];
        NSRectFill(bottom);

        NSRect topRect = NSMakeRect(NSMinX(boundingRect), NSMinY(boundingRect), NSWidth(boundingRect), 1.0);
        NSRectFill(topRect);

        [super drawGlyphsForGlyphRange:attributeGlyphRange atPoint:origin];
        [NSGraphicsContext restoreGraphicsState];
    }
    else {
        [super drawGlyphsForGlyphRange:glyphsToShow atPoint:origin];
    }
    glyphRange.length = NSMaxRange(glyphRange) - NSMaxRange(attributeGlyphRange);
    glyphRange.location = NSMaxRange(attributeGlyphRange);
}
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<h3>Setting attributes</h3>

<p>Let's turn our attention to <code>CCFMainWindowController</code> where our attributes are being managed.  When the user presses the highlight button, we want to tell the text view to apply our attribute to the selection - which is what we do in <code>setCustomAttribute:</code>:</p>

<p>``` objc
- (IBAction)setCustomAttribute:(id)sender {</p>

<pre><code>//  add our custom attribute to the selected range
NSRange selectedRange = [[self textView] selectedRange];
NSTextStorage *textStorage = self.textView.textStorage;
[textStorage addAttribute:CCFSpecialHighlightAttributeName value:[self attributeColors] range:selectedRange];
</code></pre>

<p>}</p>

<h1>pragma mark - Private</h1>

<p>//  return dictionary of highlight and line colors for our custom attribute's value
- (NSDictionary *)attributeColors {</p>

<pre><code>return @{  CCFHighlightColorKey : self.highlightColorWell.color, CCFLineColorKey : self.lineColorWell.color };
</code></pre>

<p>}</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>The rest of the code in <code>CCFMainWindowController</code> is for setup and for observing for changes in the highlight and line colors.  Using Key-value observing, we are able to detect when the colors change and re-do our markup accordingly.</p>

<p>Athough here's much more to the text system in Cocoa you should have a good starting point for custom attributes.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Target conditionals]]></title>
    <link href="http://cocoa-factory.github.com/blog/2012/10/04/target-conditionals/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-04T14:04:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://cocoa-factory.github.com/blog/2012/10/04/target-conditionals</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you hang out on Stack Overflow long enough, you're bound to see a few questions about target conditionals like <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/12132933/preprocessor-macro-for-os-x-targets">this one - Preprocessor macro for OS X targets</a>; so here's an attempt to sort it out:</p>

<h2>How do you conditionally compile for Mac and iOS platforms?</h2>

<p>This one is a little confusing because <code>TARGET_MAC_OS</code> doesn't really do what you think.</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>  Conditional                  </th>
<th> Mac OS </th>
<th> iOS device </th>
<th> iOS sim</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>  <code>TARGET_OS_MAC</code>              </td>
<td>   X    </td>
<td>    X       </td>
<td>    X    </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  <code>TARGET_OS_IPHONE</code>           </td>
<td>        </td>
<td>    X       </td>
<td>    X    </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  <code>TARGET_OS_EMBEDDED</code>         </td>
<td>        </td>
<td>    X       </td>
<td>         </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  <code>TARGET_OS_IPHONE_SIMULATOR</code> </td>
<td>        </td>
<td>            </td>
<td>    X    </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p>(Credits to Greg Parker, <a href="http://www.sealiesoftware.com/blog/archive/2010/8/16/TargetConditionalsh.html"><em>Hamster Emporium Target Conditionals</em></a> for the table)</p>

<p>If you have one block of code for Mac and another for iOS, the trick is to place the iOS condition first:</p>

<p>``` objc</p>

<h1>if TARGET_OS_IPHONE</h1>

<p>NSString *dataString = [NSString stringWithFormat:"data = %d",count];</p>

<h1>else</h1>

<p>// this compiles on Mac OS
NSString *dataString = [NSString stringWithFormat:"data = %ld",count];</p>

<h1>endif</h1>

<p>```</p>

<h2>How I support multiple iOS or Mac versions?</h2>

<p>Usually this means that the developer wants to incorporate features in a new OS version while maintaing backwards compatibility.  The solution has a few steps:</p>

<ul>
<li>Set the base SDK on the target build setting to the newest vesion that you need.</li>
<li>Set the deployment target to the oldest version that you support</li>
</ul>


<p>Having set the target build settings, we have to do some work in the code.  Let's say we want to incorporate iOS 5 features in an app that should support earlier versions, say iOS 4.3.  Then we'll set the base SDK to iOS 5+ and the deployment target to iOS 4.3.  In the code, we do something like this:</p>

<p>``` objc</p>

<h1>if __IPHONE_OS_VERSION_MAX_ALLOWED >= 50000</h1>

<p>// compile this when the target base SDK is iOS 5.0 or greater.<br/>
// We use this as a compile-time test to prevent errors if we
// try to recompile the project with a lower base SDK setting</p>

<h1>endif</h1>

<p><code>``
So far, we will be able to compile for platforms between the OS ranges specified by our lower boundary of the deployment target and our upper boundary of the base SDK.  But what happens at runtime?  We'll crash on any features above our deployment target; so we need a runtime check for class availability.  As of the iOS 4.2 SDK, you should use the</code>NSObject<code></code>class<code>method to check for the availability of weakly linked classes at runtime.  This takes advantage of the</code>NS_CLASS_AVAILABLE` macro; so in our example:</p>

<p>``` objc</p>

<h1>if __IPHONE_OS_VERSION_MAX_ALLOWED >= 50000</h1>

<p>if( [CIImage class]  ) {</p>

<pre><code>// CIImage is available in iOS 5.0
</code></pre>

<p>}</p>

<h1>endif</h1>

<p>```</p>

<p>The first check is a compile-time check to ensure that we can compile on lower SDK's and the second check is a runtime check to ensure that the weakly linked <code>CIImage</code> class is available on the device where the app is running.  Of course, we can also test for method availability instead:</p>

<p>``` objc</p>

<h1>if __IPHONE_OS_VERSION_MAX_ALLOWED >= 50000</h1>

<p>if( [UIImage respondsToSelector:@selector(someNewMethod)]  ) {</p>

<pre><code>// we can use fancy new method on UIImage
</code></pre>

<p>}</p>

<h1>endif</h1>

<p>```</p>

<h2>What is <code>__IPHONE_OS_VERSION_MIN_REQUIRED?</code></h2>

<p>Unless you set it yourself, the compiler will set it to your target deployment version.  Same for <code>__MAC_OS_VERSION_MIN_REQUIRED</code>.  But you probably guessed that already.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
